Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Newspaper Guild PE.002
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Newspaper Guild
1928-2001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.002
4 Linear Feet in 3 record cartons and 3 shared boxes
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Newspaper Guild (1928-2001) is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The collection consists largely of agreements, contracts and constitutions, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. As a whole, the material offers a general feel for the types of printed matter put out by the Guild as well as a brief introduction to and history of the Guild. In addition to the materials generated by the national body, local bodies from around the country also have material in the collection, generally agreements, contracts, and constitutions. A significant portion of the collection comes from Local 3, the Newspaper Guild of New York. The units of Local 3 are represented by workers of prominent New York newspapers, some still operational and some not, these include: The New York Times, The Daily News, The Brooklyn Daily Eagle, and The New York Post, among others.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series. All series are arranged alphabetically. The series arrangement of the records is as follows:
Series I: National Guild Files, 1937-1995
Series II: Newspaper Guild of New York, Local 3 Files, 1928-2001
Series III: Other Local Files, 1941-1990
Historical Note
The Newspaper Guild, founded by Heywood Broun in 1933 as the American Newspaper Guild, was first conceived primarily as a craft union for editorial staff. After gaining convention approval for a broader base, the structure of the Guild changed considerably. It grew to have more of an industrial trade union structure, organizing not only reporters and editorial staff, but workers in all areas of print production, including advertising, accounting, and circulation. In the 1970s, the Guild dropped the "American" and simply became the Newspaper Guild and in 1995, merged with the Communication Workers of America. As of 2009, the Newspaper Guild had over 34,000 members in the United States and Canada.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Newspaper Guild (1928-2001) consists of agreements, contracts, constitutions, by-laws, and reports, as well as printed ephemera such as fliers, brochures, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications.
Series I: National Guild Files (1937-1995) consists of material that was generated by both the American Newspaper Guild and the later named Newspaper Guild. The American Newspaper Guild files range in date from 1937 to 1970 when the Guild changed its name, and consist of agreements and contracts, constitutions, and collective bargaining manuals. In addition to a number of pamphlets on the history of Guild, there are range of other pamphlets in the collection about the organizing campaigns of the union, the history and effectiveness of trade union papers as organizing tools, and the supply and demand of newsprint. Files from the Newspaper Guild range in date from 1971-1995 and consist of constitutions, convention proceedings and reports, collective bargaining manuals, and pension plan publications as well as material put out by a rank and file group called "Concerned Guild Members." There are also a few newspaper clippings and reprinted articles from the Guild's own Guild Reporter on their collective bargaining plans and women in the workforce.
Series II: Newspaper Guild of New York, Local 3 Files (1928-2001) consists of agreements and contracts with various New York newspapers and publishers as well as printed ephemera. There are a number of pamphlets and publications in the collection outlining a range of issues including the history of the local, the profit system of the newspaper industry, women in the workplace and the strike at and closure of The Brooklyn Daily Eagle. The collection also includes fliers, brochures, open letters, and bumper stickers produced by Local 3, as well as material from the rank and file Committee for Guild Democracy and the Committee for Guild Unity pertaining to union elections in support of their non-communist slate.
Series III: Other Local Files (1941-1990) consists largely of agreements and contracts generated by locals from around the country. The local files consist of material under the affiliation of both the American Newspaper Guild and the Newspaper Guild. Some of the earliest contracts the Guild established with newspapers around the country can be found in the collection.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Newspaper Guild of New York Records (WAG 125)
Newspaper Guild of New York: Betsy Wade Files (WAG 45)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library.
In 2025, materials from accession 2019.056, which is associated with Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on Subjects (PE 029), were transferred to this collection.
Labor unions -- United States -- Newspapers.; Labor unions; Fliers (printed matter); Contracts; Broadsides (notices); Constitutions.; Articles.; Collective bargaining.; Agreements.; Bylaws (administrative records); Pamphlets.; Strikes and lockouts.; Publications (documents); Labor -- New York (State) -- New York -- Newspapers.; Press releases.; Labor unions -- United States.; Labor -- United States -- Periodicals.; Circular letters.; Newspaper Guild of New York; American Newspaper Guild; Newspaper Guild
- Series I: National Guild Files, 1937-1995; 1.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 2 oversize shared boxes.
  - American Newspaper Guild: Agreements and Contracts I, 1957, 1959 (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Agreements and Contracts II, 1957, 1959 (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Annual Convention: Programs, 1941-1944 (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Circular Letters, 1946 (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Constitutions I, 1937, 1959-1970 (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Constitutions II, 1937, 1959-1970 (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Fliers, circa 1940s, undated (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Manuals I, 1940-1961, undated (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Manuals II, 1940-1961, undated (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1948-1951 (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Pamphlets and Publications, 1940-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - American Newspaper Guild: Pension Plan, 1967 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Circular Letters, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: "Concerned Guild Members", 1992-1993 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Constitutions, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Constitutions, 1975-1979 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Constitutions, 1980-1984 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Constitutions, 1985-1989 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Constitutions, 1990-1995 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Conventions: Proceedings and Programs, 1978-1983, 1995 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Department of Research and Information: Publications, 1974-1990 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Ephemera, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Manuals, 1988, 1991, undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Manuals: Collective Bargaining (I), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Manuals: Collective Bargaining (II), 1980 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Newspaper Clippings and Articles on, 1979, 1991 (Box 1, Box Shared Tamiment 007, Folder 11)
  - Newspaper Guild: Pamphlets and Publications, 1973-1990, undated (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Pension Fund/Pension Plan, 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Newspaper Guild: Posters (Daily News and Labor Day parade), undated (Box Shared Tamiment MSOS003)
- Series II: Newspaper Guild of New York, Local 3 Files, 1928-2001; 1 linear foot in 1 record carton
  - Agreements and Contracts: Brooklyn Daily Eagle, 1939, 1950-1952 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Consumers Union of United States, 1957-1981 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: El Diario - La Pensa, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Free Europe Committee, Inc., 1957-1967 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Hearst Publishing Company, Inc., 1953-1959 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Long Island Daily Press, 1955-1964 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Herald Tribune, 1952-1962 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Journal-American, 1946-1948, 1956-1958 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Mirror, 1946-1956 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York News Inc., 1970-1987 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Post Corporation, 1949-1967 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Post Corporation, 1970-1984 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Times Company, 1948-1967 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Times Company, 1970-1981 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York Tribune Inc., 1946, 1949 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: New York World-Telegram and Sun, 1950-1962 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: News Syndicate Co. Inc., 1940-1946, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Newsweek, Inc., 1962-1983 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Reuters Limited, 1971, 1980 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Saturday Review, Inc., 1969 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Scientific American, 1968-1979 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Standard and Poor's Corporation, 1959-1980 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Time, Inc., 1964-1983 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Triangle Publications, Inc., 1967, 1970 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: Weekly Publications, Inc., 1952-1957 (Box 2)
  - Agreements and Contracts: World Journal Tribune, 1966 (Box 2)
  - Annual Convention, 1947-1984, undated (Box 2)
  - By-laws, 1945-1978, undated (Box 2)
  - Circular Letters, 1941-1980, undated (Box 2)
  - Committee for Guild Unity, undated (Box 2)
  - Elections (Union), 1948, 1978, 1988, undated (Box 2)
  - Fliers and Ephemera, 1940-1944, undated (Box 2)
  - Newsletters (Various Units), 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Articles and Publications Relating to, 1948, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications, 1940-1970, circa 1981, undated (Box 2)
  - Pension Plan/Health Benefits, 1957-1983 (Box 2)
  - Photographs, 1983-1984 (Box 2)
  - Press Releases, 1952-1954, undated (Box 2)
  - Rank and File, 1948-1949, 1993, undated (Box 2)
  - Units: Consumers Union, 1950, 1980, 2001 (Box 2)
  - Units: Daily News, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Units: Daily News, 1990-1993, undated (Box 2)
  - Units: Long Island Press, 1937, undated (Box 2)
  - Units: New York Post, 1993 (Box 2)
  - Units: New York Times, 1928, 1969, 1978-1984 (Box 2)
  - Units: World-Telegram and Sun, 1934, 1948-1952, undated (Box 2)
- Series III: Other Local Files, 1941-1990; 1.5 Linear Feet in 1 record carton and 1 shared manuscript box
  - Chicago Newspaper Guild (Hearst Strike Committee), c. 1938 (Box 3, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 1)
  - Local 32 (Newspaper Guild of Boston), 1943-1944 (Box 3, Box Shared Tamiment 190, Folder 2)
  - Local 35 (Washington-Baltimore Newspaper Guild), 1966-1974 (Box 3)
  - Local 41 (Providence Newspaper Guild), 1978 (Box 3)
  - Local 52 (San Francisco-Oakland Newspaper Guild), 1941, 1977 (Box 3)
  - Local 74 (Denver Newspaper Guild), 1988 (Box 3)
  - Local 82 (Pacific Northwest Newspaper Guild), 1990 (Box 3)
  - Local 91 (Memphis Newspaper Guild), 1977, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Local 95 (San Diego Newspaper Guild), 1979 (Box 3)
  - Local 120 (Newspaper Guild of Wilkes-Barre), 1954 (Box 3)
  - Local 128 (Portland Newspaper Guild), 1974, 1979 (Box 3)
  - Local 202 (Bakersfield Newspaper Guild), 1977 (Box 3)
  - Local 222 (Wire Service Guild), 1976, 1983, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Local 223 (Victoria Newspaper Guild), undated (Box 3)
  - Los Angeles Newspaper Guild, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Guild of Albany (New York), 1973 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Guild of Detroit, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Newspaper Guild of Pittsburgh, 1941 (Box 3)
  - St. Louis Newspaper Guild, 1969 (Box 3)
  - Tri-City Newspaper Guild, 1947 (Box 3)